Guide to the Nathanael Greene Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Nathanael Greene papers
1774-1793
MS 616
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
0.5
Thirty-one manuscript letters to Nathanael Greene, one photostatic copy and two volumes of typed transcripts of letters and Revolutionary War era documents. The originals of these transcripts were formerly owned by William A. Reed and are now in the Clements Library of the University of Michigan.
Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Duncan H. Read, 1967.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This small but important collection of Nathanael Greene papers consists of thirty-one original letters, one photostatic copy, and two volumes of typed transcripts of letters exchanged by Greene and Revolutionary War officers, government officials, family members, and others between 1774 and 1793. There is also a volume of typed transcripts of Revolutionary War era documents containing letters by George Washington, Nathan Hale, William Hooper, and others, the roll of minute-men of Bridgewater, Massachusetts, military commissions, and so forth. The volumes of transcripts are copies of original documents and letters formerly owned by William A. Read and now in Clements Library of the University of Michigan. The volumes and the thirty-one original letters were given to Yale University by Duncan Read in 1967.
The Greene papers are of great value to students of the American Revolution and for those interested in Greene's life.
Further correspondence of Nathanael Greene can be found in the Bernhard Knollenberg Collection, Manuscript Group Number 26.
United States -- History -- Revolution, 1775-1783; Soldiers; Flagg, Henry Collins, 1742-1801; Garden, Alexander, 1757-1829; Greene, Christopher, 1737-1781; Greene, Griffin, 1749-1804; Greene, Jacob; Greene, Nathanael, 1742-1786; Greene, William, 1731-1809; Huntington, Samuel, 1731-1796; Irvine, John; Littlefield, William; Morris, Lewis, 1726-1798; Pettit, Charles, 1736-1806; Wooster, Thomas, 1751-1792; Hewes & Anthony
- Inventory
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence is organized alphabetically by name. Bracketed information includes the number of letters to Nathanael Greene/from Nathanael Greene.
  - Brown, John [0/1], 1778 September 6 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Congress, President of [Elias Boudinot, 0/1], 1783 July 10 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ellery, William [0/1], 1785 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Flagg, Henry Collins [1/0], 1784 May 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Garden, Alexander [2/0], 1783 June 20, August 3 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Greene, Catharine (Mrs. Nathanael) [0/1], 1785 May 25 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Greene, Christopher [2/0], 1783 May 19, [1785 Sep?] (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Greene, Griffin [4/0], 1780 [1783?] May 18, 1784 November 2, 1785 December 10, 22 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Greene, Jacob [1/0], 1784 April 3 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Greene, William [1/0], 1783 December 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hancock, Major General [0/1], 1778 September 30 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hewes & Anthony (bill) [1/0], 1784 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Huntington, Samuel [1/0], 1780 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Irvine, John [1/0], 1786 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lafayette, Marie Joseph, marquis [0/1], 1784 March 24 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lee, Gen. Henry [0/1], 1783 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Littlefield, William [4/0], 1785 April 25, December 16, 28, 1786 May 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Morris, Lewis [1/0], 1785 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Pettit, Charles [1/1], 1779 May 10, 1783 December 12 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Trumbull, John [0/1, photostat copy], 1780 January 22 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Washington, George [0/1], 1779 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Wayne, General [0/1], 1784 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Wooster, Thomas [1/0], 1785 August 29 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Revolutionary Correspondence of General Nathanael Greene"
    - Vol. I: "Letters by General Greene Addressed to His Wife and Others, 1779-1785
      - Typed transcripts (Box 1, Folder 24)
      - Carbon with corrections (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Vol. II: "Letters Addressed to General and Mrs. Greene by Prominent Men of the American Revolution", 1778-1793
      - Typed transcripts (Box 1, Folder 26)
      - Carbon with corrections (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - "Revolutionary Documents and Letters" [typed transcripts], 1774-1793 (Box 1, Folder 28)